The violence of our time is caused by obedience. Throughout American history,
the political leaders have always exhorted the American people to be nice
and quiet and leave things to them. But when very serious evils confronted the
American people, they had to go beyond the congressmen and the senators and they
had to commit civil disobedience and they had even to break the law. And the
abolitionists had to do it and right here in Boston they had to violate federal
law by trying to bring a slave away from the federal marshals. They had to commit
civil disobedience. The labor movement had to do this. They had to violate the law.
They had to disrupt things. They had to do all sorts of impolite things. They had the
sit-ins of sit-down strikes of 1936 and 37. And only this finally brought that
modicum of justice that the labor movement demanded. And the civil rights movement
went through the same thing. And you know that Congress did not act on the civil
rights laws of sixty-three, of sixty-four and sixty-five until blacks went out into
the streets and made a commotion. They did not do it on the basis of some polite
discourse. You know we have brought, been brought up to believe that the American
political system works beautifully. It is democratic. Congress represents us. The
president is elected. He represents us. It doesn't work that way. Democracy depends on
people speaking out, and in times of great crisis, on people creating a commotion.